<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on GOV 1347: Election Analytics Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on GOV 1347: Election Analytics Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/election-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Forecast 09/30/2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/29/week-4-forecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/29/week-4-forecast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Week 4: September 30, 2024&lt;/h1&gt;  &#xA;This blog is an ongoing project for Professor Ryan Enos&#39; Election Analytics Course at Harvard College (GOV 1347, Fall 2024). It will be updated weekly with posts analyzing how different features impact the likelihood of Kamala Harris (D) or Donald Trump (R) winning the 2024 U.S. Presidential Election or winning specific states in the election. The blog will culminate in a final predictive model for the outcome of the general election.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Context &amp; Question&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;In the 18 elections since the end of World War II (1948), incumbent candidates have won a third of them. But considering that the incumbent president has only run in 11 of those elections, the statistic comes out to be that the incumbent won in about **two-thirds** of elections in which they were running. So this week&#39;s blog explores whether incumbency really matters in a presidential race, and whether it&#39;s a good prediction of an election outcome. We can measure &#34;incumbency&#34; both on the basis of the candidate and the party. This is especially interesting in the 2024 race because one candidate (Donald Trump) is not a *direct* incumbent, meaning he did not serve in the pevious term, but he has served before. And the other candidate (Kamala Harris) is a member of the incumbent party *and* incumbent administration, but is not a president seeking re-election.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;The Data&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;I&#39;ll use data about the popular vote in each state since 1948 to determine whether incumbents performed consistently well or poorly in certain states over time, or whether their performance in different states was subject to the volatility in states (i.e. is incumbent performance consistent even in states considered &#34;battleground&#34; between parties?)&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, I decided to investigate whether particular states tend to vote for incumbent parties more often than others. The maps below show each state that voted for an incumbent party versus a challenger party&amp;rsquo;s candidate in every election since 1948.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecast 09/21/2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/21/week-3-forecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/21/week-3-forecast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Week 3: September 23, 2024&lt;/h1&gt;  &#xA;This blog is an ongoing project for Professor Ryan Enos&#39; Election Analytics Course at Harvard College (GOV 1347, Fall 2024). It will be updated weekly with posts analyzing how different features impact the likelihood of Kamala Harris (D) or Donald Trump (R) winning the 2024 U.S. Presidential Election or winning specific states in the election. The blog will culminate in a final predictive model for the outcome of the general election.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Context &amp; Question&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;Since the 19th century, polls have been conducted to predict the outcomes of U.S. presidential elections. While they ultimately predict a binary outcome (i.e. will candidate A win or lose the election), they usually convey their results in percentages (i.e. what percent of the vote can candidate A expect to receive, what percent chance does candidate A have of victory). Polls do this at both the national level and the state level. The results are publicly disseminated, usually in newspapers. in addition to informing the electorate, they may influence voter behavior or motivation. This post asks whether polls (national or state) that show two candidates close to each other correspond to higher turnout rates and vice versa: whether polls that show one candidate defeating the other by a high margin actually discourage turnout (with voters reasoning that their opinion will not shift the result). If polls do cause turnout rates to change, they may also cause the results they&#39;re predicting to flesh out differently (if not every individual polled shows up to vote, then the results they contributed to forecasting will likely vary in reality).  &#xA;In this week&#39;s blog post, I analyze a set of presidential polling averages by state from 1968 through 2024 to (1) evaluate whether close polls are associated with higher or lower voter turnout and (2) evaluate whether polls that forecast close races should adjust for turnout in one direction, and polls that forecast landslide results the other. Recognizing that &#34;should&#34; is subjective, I use it to evaluate whether the poll would be more accurate compared to the actual result if adjusted for turnout (high or low).&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;The Data&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;In this post, I convey polling averages in three datasets. The first contains candidates&#39; polling averages from 1968-2016, the second contains the data from 2020, and the third contains the data from 2024. Each dataset is structured the same. They each contain a mix of nation-wide and state-wide polls and provide a percentage estimate for how much of the vote, in the nation or in the specified state, a candidate will receive. the particular candidate is named in a separate column. There is also a column in which the vote-share estimate is adjusted for national trends, but I choose to focus on the regular, raw percent estimates in this analysis.&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;# load data--polling averages&#xA;avg_68_16 &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;pres_pollaverages_1968-2016.csv&amp;quot;)&#xA;avg_20 &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;pres_pollaverages_2020.csv&amp;quot;)&#xA;avg_24 &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;pres_pollaverages_2024.csv&amp;quot;)&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pr</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecast 09/16/2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/16/week-2-forecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/16/week-2-forecast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Week 2: September 16, 2024&lt;/h1&gt;  &#xA;This blog is an ongoing project for Professor Ryan Enos&#39; Election Analytics Course at Harvard College (GOV 1347, Fall 2024). It will be updated weekly with posts analyzing how different features impact the likelihood of Kamala Harris (D) or Donald Trump (R) winning the 2024 U.S. Presidential Election or winning specific states in the election. The blog will culminate in a final predictive model for the outcome of the general election.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Context &amp; Question&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;In his successful 1992 campaign for the U.S. Presidency, Bill Clinton is quoted as saying &#34;it&#39;s the economy, stupid.&#34; Clinton implied that, in a strong economy, voters would favor an incumbent candidate/party, and vice versa in a weak economy. There are several philosophies about what constitutes a &#34;strong economy.&#34; Changes in GDP, in GDP per capita, unemployment rate, and inflation rate are all indicators. In this post, I&#39;m interested in looking at the strength of the U.S. Dollar (USD) relative to the currencies of major trading partners and allies, and seeing if it holds predictive power in presidential elections.  &#xA;&lt;h2&gt;The Data&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;The Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis publishes the daily exchange rates between the U.S. dollar and a variety of other currencies. I chose to use data about the Japanese Yen, the Chinese Yuan Renminbi, the British Pound, and the Euro. The span of data available for each currency is summarized below:&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Currency&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Start of Data&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Japanese Yen&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;January 4, 1971&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;British Pound&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;January 4, 1971&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Chinese Yuan&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;January 2, 1981&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Euro&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;January 4, 1999&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The American Economy is linked to the Japanese Yen through carry-trading. The Yen has historically had no interest rate, making it an attractive currency for investors to buy, place in stocks or bonds, and then exchange for USD (or another foreign currency) before collecting the returns on their investments. However, changes in the value of the Yen can send the U.S. stock market into turmoil, as happened in the first week of August, 2024. Another reason to use the Yen is the mutual defense agreement between the U.S. and Japan. Though remnant of the post-World War II era, part of this agreement&amp;rsquo;s appeal is that the U.S. earns a profit selling defense technology to Japan. In doing so, it bolsters the nation&amp;rsquo;s capacity to defend itself and reduces the chance that the U.S. will have to intervene. In this sense fluctuations in the Yen can be foreboding about the U.S. economy. A weak Yen may cost the U.S. in defense exports, and simultaneously make U.S. intervention in Japan seem more likely, especially in the face of rising tensions between China and Taiwan, and the North Korean threat in southeast Asia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecast 09/09/2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/09/forecast-09-09-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/post/2024/09/09/forecast-09-09-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Week 1: September 9, 2024&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;This blog is an ongoing project for Professor Ryan Enos&#39; Election Analytics Course at Harvard College (GOV 1347, Fall 2024). It will be updated weekly with posts analyzing how different features impact the likelihood of Kamala Harris (D) or Donald Trump (R) winning the 2024 U.S. Presidential Election or winning specific states in the election. The blog will culminate in a final predictive model for the outcome of the general election. Some posts, such as this one, will examine the state of existing polls and try to explain variation between them.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;While keeping up with predictions for the upcoming presidential election and making my own, I find myself float towards newspapers and media outlets. I consider myself an avid consumer of journalism, and find newspapers reliable for updated polling information. But I know that this is not true of all individuals in the electorate. In this post, I wonder if events that make headlines matter as much to voters as they do to polling agencies. That is, are pollsters are justified when they survey the electorate after a major event, or do the events reported on impact the views of their populations less than it impacted their thoguht processes. I&#39;d imagine that polls sponsored by news organizations tend to undergo updates after *those same* news organizations publish major stories, so I&#39;d like to see if sponsored polls yield similar results to each other.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;The Data&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;The New York Times&#39; 2024 Election Poll Tracker is updated daily with predictions for candidate performance based on aggregate results from of nation-wide and state-specific surveys. The surveys it uses are collected and displayed in a table on the poll tracker&#39;s website. I scraped these surveys from the Times&#39; website into a JSON file with fields such as the pollster&#39;s name, whether the poll had any sponsorship, and the poll&#39;s results. Then I wrote a simple Python script to convert the JSON file into a CSV format (election-blog/jsontocsv.py) Then I looked for differences in the estimates of polls sponsored by external agencies/organizations versus those not sponsored at all. In a future analysis, I hope to compare polls sponsored by news outlets to polls sponsored by other organizations (e.g. colleges, universities), but due to the limited sample size (The New York Times only provided 50 polls because it did not include any polls that began earlier than August 6, 2024. Only 17 of them were sponsored at all) I chose to compare polls sponsored by *any* entity to those run by independent pollsters in this post.&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Methods/Analyses&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;# install packages&#xA;library(ggplot2)&#xA;library(maps)&#xA;library(tidyverse)&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pr</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2024 Election Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/election-blog/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Catherine Stanton and I&amp;rsquo;m a senior at Harvard College studying statistics and government. My professional interests lie in the use of data science for natonal intelligence and cybersecurity, but I&amp;rsquo;m also passionate about American politics, civic education, and electoral accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this blog is to post forecasts and models about the 2024 U.S. General Election as a part of Professor Ryan Enos&amp;rsquo; GOV 1347 course. Given that Kamala Harris is the second female candidate to face Donald Trump in the last decade, I&amp;rsquo;m especially interested in models that acknowledge similarities between the Harris and Clinton campaigns and are intentionally designed such that sources of error from 2016 do not reappear in new models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
